Guide to the Deep Dish TV Records MSS.312
Fales Library and Special Collections
Deep Dish TV Records
1980-2021
Fales Library and Special Collections
Deep Dish TV Network
MSS.312
134 Linear Feet in 78.5 manuscript boxes, 64 record cartons, 45 upright video containers, 20 cassette boxes, 16 LP boxes, 5 flat boxes, 4 CD boxes, 5 custom boxes for physical digital media, and 1 flat file folder
1124 MiniDV
539 U-matic
95 1_Inch_Video_Reel
87 Betacam_SP
59 DVCAM
1 DVCPRO
33 VHS
26 Betacam
5 Hi8
3 audiocassettes
2.16 Terabytes in 12,075 digital files
7 websites in 7 archived websites.
Deep Dish Television, launched in 1986 by Paper Tiger Television, was a distribution network committed to exploring new and democratic ways of promoting video artwork and reporting. Their programs connected artists, independent videomakers, programmers, and social activists, and covered topics such as women's rights, the environmental movement, the U.S. healthcare system, U.S. elections, the Iraq War and the Gulf War, the Israeli-Palestinian Conflict, the World Trade Organization, the prison industrial complex, media censorship, and racism and colonialism worldwide. The Deep Dish TV Records (1980-2021) contain video broadcast masters from 1986-2018, source material such as interview and event footage, and production files detailing the process of funding, staffing, researching, writing, shooting, and editing programs. The collection also contains materials related to the Network's administration, interaction with viewers, participation in events such as film festivals and conferences, publicity, political advocacy, and relationships with other independent media organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection donated by Deep Dish TV in 2011. In April of 2016 an addition to the collection was donated by Brian Drolet on behalf of Deep Dish TV; the accession number associated with this gift is 2016.022. In August 2018 an additional accretion was donated; the accession number associated with this gift is 2018.098. A further accretion was donated in August 2022; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.003.
http://www.deepdishtv.org/, https://deepdishtvuprooted.wordpress.com/, and http://www.deepdishwavesofchange.org/ were initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2009 as part of the Alternative Mass Media / News Web Sites Web Archive. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2015, crawling was discontinued in the Alternative Mass Media / News Web Sites Web Archive and began being captured in the Fales Library: Deep Dish TV Web Archive. In 2018, http://www.deepdishtv.org/ redirected to http://catalog.deepdishtv.org/catalogue/ and was added to the web archive. The accession number associated with the redirect is 2019.070. In 2019, http://www.deepdishwavesofchange.org/ and http://weinterruptthisprogram.org/ was added to the web archive. The accession numbers associated with these websites is 2019.053 and 2019.057. In 2020, the original https://deepdishtv.org/ was revived and http://ddtv-stage.herokuapp.com/ was added to the collection. The accession number associated with these websites are 2021.006.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the repository email.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Appraisal
In August 2023, 7 linear feet of paper materials were deaccessioned, including duplicate materials, sensitive financial and legal documents, and materials outside the scope of the collection. Two blank miniDV tapes were also deaccessioned.
In September 2024, 2 videotapes were deaccessioned as they were found to contain duplicative content.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I. Video Productions
Series II. Administrative Files
Series III. Events
Series IV. Publicity
Series V. Subject Files
Historical Note
Deep Dish Television was the first grassroots satellite network in the United States, committed to exploring new and democratic ways of promoting video artwork and reporting. The network was launched in 1986 by Paper Tiger Television, a volunteer-based video collective that has produced public access programming since 1981. From 1986 to 2018, Deep Dish TV produced and distributed television series on a variety of cultural and political topics. Their programs linked the work of artists, independent videomakers, programmers, and social activists and reached millions of people through public access channels.
Deep Dish TV produced and distributed programs on a wide variety of issues. Starting with their Opening Series in 1986, their programs investigated labor and immigration (Beyond the Browning of America, Siempre Trabajando: Latinos and Labor), environmental justice (Green Screen: Grassroots Views of the Environmental Crisis), censorship (Writers Uncensored and Behind Censorship: The Assault on Civil Liberties), the prison industrial complex (Emergency Programming: Mumia Abu-Jamal, America Behind Bars, and Lock Down USA), the U.S. healthcare system (Sick and Tired of Being Sick and Tired), and the Gulf War (The Gulf Crisis TV Project). They also explored international video activism with …Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia, Unheard Voices, and Rock the Boat.
From 2003-2005, Deep Dish TV broadcasted the series Shocking and Awful: A Grassroots Response to War and Occupation investigating the impact of the U.S. invasion of Iraq. The series was later featured at the Whitney Museum of American Art's 2006 Biennial Exhibition and the Museum of Modern Art's "Theater of Operations: Gulf Wars 1991-2011" exhibition from 2019-2020. Deep Dish TV became known for their criticism of the Iraq War, and later produced extensive coverage of the World Tribunal on Iraq (Istanbul, 2005), the International Commission of Inquiry on Crimes Against Humanity of the Bush Administration (New York City, 2005-2006), and the Winter Soldier Eyewitness Accounts of the Iraq and Afghanistan Occupations (organized by the Iraq Veterans Against the War, 2008). They also criticized the Bush administration's handling of Hurricane Katrina and highlighted resistance in New Orleans with the series Trouble the Water (2006).
Throughout the 2000s, Deep Dish TV covered the Israeli occupations of Palestine ("Imperial Geography," c. 2005) and Lebanon (Nothing is Safe, 2007). In the 2010s, they focused on social movements in the United States with DIY Media: Movement Perspectives on Critical Moments (2011), Uprooted: A Grassroots Examination of the Politics of Migration (2011), An American Nightmare: Black Labor and Liberation (2015), and We Interrupt This Program (2018). They also highlighted community media around the world in the interactive series Waves of Change: The Many Voices of a Global Village (2011).
In addition to their television programming, Deep Dish TV frequently organized and participated in film festivals, conferences, screenings, panel discussions, and exhibitions. They organized speaking tours across the United States to promote Not Channel Zero (1993-1995), "Iraqi Women Speak Out" (2006), and "Environmental Justice for All" (2006). They also organized a conference in 2010 titled "Re-Igniting the Network: Video and New Technology in the Service of Social Movements."
Deep Dish TV had a history of collaboration with other independent media organizations and advocacy for public access media. Deep Dish TV produced the first year of the television version of Democracy Now! with Amy Goodman and Juan Gonzalez; they played a large role in founding the Indymedia Center in Seattle, and have worked to expand that network in Africa, Asia, and Latin America; they had a close working relationship with Free Speech TV and LinkTV; and they collaborated with numerous independent media organizations within their television programming, including the series DIVA TV: Collections from this Activist Collective (broadcasted in the Spring of 1990), Black Planet Productions' Not Channel Zero (broadcasted in 1992), Seattle Independent Media Center's Showdown in Seattle (broadcasted in 1999), and Washington DC's Independent Media Center's Breaking the Bank (broadcasted in 1999). Deep Dish TV was also active in the Access for All coalition in the mid 1990s, composed of individuals and organizations working to educate and organize New Yorkers on the topic of universal, equitable, and affordable telecommunications systems. Fiscally sponsored by Media Network, the coalition conducted media literacy workshops throughout New York City.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
The Deep Dish TV Records (1980-2021) contain audiovisual, paper, and digital materials documenting the public access network's productions, administration, event participation, publicity, media advocacy, and relationships with other media and political organizations. In addition to the production and organizational history of Deep Dish TV, the Deep Dish TV Records document the political topics that Deep Dish investigated, as well as the independent media scene and its most active members from the 1980s-2010s. Frequent collaborators include Paper Tiger TV, Free Speech TV, Democracy Now!, DIVA TV, Indymedia, and Alternative Radio.
The production history of Deep Dish TV from their 1986 Opening Series to their 2018 series We Interrupt This Program is reflected in this collection's broadcast masters, dubs, source footage and media elements on analog and digital video. Corresponding paper and digital files portray the production process in a range of documents, including calls for submissions, program proposals, budgets and expenses, projected timelines, production and licensing contracts, correspondence with producers, video stills, graphics, and cover art design.
This collection includes thorough documentation of the day-to-day administrative activities of Deep Dish TV, including Board of Directors and Steering Committee minutes, memoranda, and notes; financial documents such as budgets and expenses; fundraising strategy and related documentation such as merchandise sales and grant applications; mail received from viewers and mailing lists for outgoing communications; contact lists for research and outreach on a variety of subjects; carriage lists detailing the television stations that carry Deep Dish programs; and internal staff correspondence, job descriptions, and staff biographies.
Deep Dish TV's participation in numerous film festivals, video screenings, speaking tours, conferences, and exhibitions is reflected in paper and digital files such as event ephemera, awards, photographs, and audiovisual recordings.
Promotional materials, advertisements, and publicity for Deep Dish TV's programs and activities are also represented in this collection. These paper and digital files include press releases, press clippings, program directories, mock-ups for logos and graphics, flyers and posters for Deep Dish programs, outreach to producers, programmers, and viewers, files related to marketing and advertising, and demo reels, samplers, and PSAs recorded in analog and digital video.
The Deep Dish TV Records also hold research files compiled by the Deep Dish staff. These paper and digital files include press clippings and notes on topics related to independent media advocacy, political activism, and world events. They also include ephemera, correspondence, and promotional materials from a variety of television networks and media organizations that were also active in the public access scene. These files were referenced by the staff for research, networking, distribution and outreach.
Custodial History
This collection was donated to Fales by Deep Dish TV in 2011, 2016, and 2018.
In 2007, Deep Dish TV hired a vendor to digitize and create MiniDV copies of all master 1" open reel videotapes and U-matic videotapes. An internal report notes that the transfer was not completely accurate and had some errors. The digitzed files were uploaded to the Internet Archive.
Television broadcasting.; Public Access Television -- New York.; Public-access television -- United States; Asian Americans in television broadcasting.; African Americans in television; Documentary television programs.; Television producers and directors.; Gay and lesbian film festivals. -- 21st century; Alternative mass media -- United States; AIDS (Disease) and mass media.; Feminism and mass media.; Labor unions and mass media.; Mass media and culture.; Women in mass media.; Environmental justice.; Prison-industrial complex; Health care reform; Iraq War, 2003-2011; Persian Gulf War, 1991.; Emigration and immigration -- History -- United States.; Elections -- United States.; Protest movements -- United States.; Paper Tiger Television Collective (Firm); Democracy Now! (Organization); Free Speech TV; Halleck, DeeDee
- Series I. Video Productions, 1982-2018; 13.5 Linear Feet in 17 manuscript boxes and 5 flat boxes; 906 MiniDV; 470 U-matic; 93 1_Inch_Video_Reel; 81 Betacam_SP; 26 Betacam; 58 DVCAM; 27 VHS; 5 Hi8; 3 audiocassettes; 1.538 Terabytes in 6,117 files
  Arrangement
  Series I. Video Productions (1982-2018) is arranged chronologically, with recordings and files from each Deep Dish series (i.e. Sick and Tired of Being Sick and Tired) grouped together. Wherever possible, file names for video recordings are taken directly from videotape labels and edited minimally for accessibility. Series titles are italicized, and episode titles are in quotations. Videotapes that contain multiple programs are titled "Compilation Tapes" with a list of all programs included in a Scope and Contents Note. Producers and program contributors have been noted in a Scope and Contents Note when known.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Video Productions (1982-2018) contains materials related to the television programs produced and distributed by Deep Dish TV. This series contains analog and digital video recordings of programs, including masters, dubs, source footage such as interviews and event coverage, and recordings used during production such as graphics and credits. This series also contains paper and digital production files that document the production process. The production files include a large variety of documents such as calls for submissions, proposals, budgets, expenses, projected timelines, production and licensing contracts, release forms, correspondence with producers, bios of producers, production related expenses, research, video stills, graphics, and cover art design.
  - Carol Mansour Interview, Beirut, June, 1982 (Box 149, Minidv 312_1075)
  - "History of Public Access: The Early Years, '72-'74, The Struggle for a Voice", September, 1985 (Box 137, U-matic 312_1414)
    Produced by Claire Beach, Charlie Tesch, Somerville Producers Group
  - "The First Satellite Public Access Show", circa 1985 (Box 128, U-matic 312_0573)
    Presented by Boston Film/Video Foundation and Paper Tiger Television, NY
  - The Opening Series -- Program Submissions, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Opening Series -- "Central America Comes to Middle America", 1986; cuid39289 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0092, Box 91, U-matic 312_0141, Box 144, Minidv 312_0673, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_2)
    Produced by Martha Wallner
  - The Opening Series -- "Getting a Grip on Access", 1986; cuid39290 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0098, Box 144, Minidv 312_0708, Box 140, U-matic 312_1823, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_3)
    Coordinated by Diana Agosta, Andrew Blau, David Shulman
  - The Opening Series -- "Give Peace A Channel", 1986; cuid39291 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0093, Box 91, U-matic 312_0140, Box 144, Minidv 312_0672, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_4)
    Coordinated by Caryn Rogoff and Kirk Ruebenson
  - The Opening Series -- "Kids Playback: TV Made by Children", 1986; cuid39292 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0096, Box 144, Minidv 312_0669, Box 140, U-matic 312_1822, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_5)
    Coordinated by Karen Einstein & Dee Dee Halleck
  - The Opening Series -- "Labor Produces: Access to Solidarity", 1986; cuid39293 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0097, Box 137, U-matic 312_1415, Box 140, U-matic 312_1824, Box 144, Minidv 312_0712, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_6)
  - The Opening Series -- "Mediums Well Done: Remaking Popular Culture", 1986; cuid39294 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0089, Box 91, U-matic 312_0143, Box 144, Minidv 312_0676, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_7)
    Coordinated by William Brody and Marisa Bowe
  - The Opening Series -- "Racism on Main Street: A Look Around Your Corner", 1986; cuid39295 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0094, Box 91, U-matic 312_0139, Box 144, Minidv 312_0671, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_8)
  - The Opening Series -- "That's Woman's Work! TV By and About Women", 1986; cuid39296 (Box 140, U-matic 312_1828, Box 144, Minidv 312_0675, Box 87, U-matic 312_0090, Box 135, U-matic 312_1390, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_9)
  - The Opening Series -- "There's No Place Like Home: Housing Crisis USA", 1986; cuid39297 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0095, Box 144, Minidv 312_0670, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_10)
  - The Opening Series -- "This Land Is Our Land: The Farming Crisis in the USA", 1986; cuid39298 (Box 87, U-matic 312_0091, Box 91, U-matic 312_0142, Box 144, Minidv 312_0674, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_11)
    Coordinated by Joan Jubela and Dan Marcus
  - The Opening Series -- "Uh Oh Plutonium", 1986; cuid39416 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_12)
  - The Opening Series -- Release Forms, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2, 3, 4)
  - Opening Animation, 1986; cuid39415 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_1)
  - Opening Animation Slides, circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Program Stills -- Contact Sheet, circa 1986-1990 (Box 78, Folder 1)
  - Program Stills, circa 1986-2013; cuid39277 (Box 2, Folder 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_13)
  - General Production Notes, circa 1986-2013 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Protest Photographs and Program Stills, circa 1986-2013 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Video Cover and Label Designs, circa 1986-2013; cuid39278 (Box 2, Folder 8, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_15)
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "A Dish of Central America" -- Production File, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "A Dish of Central America", June 14, 1988; cuid39299 (Box 93, U-matic 312_0207, Box 144, Minidv 312_0685, 312_0695, Box 145, Minidv 312_0738, Box 173, 1 inch video reel 312_0183, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_21)
    Coordinated by Michael Murphy and Danielle Villegas for the Empowerment Project
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "Biting the Hand That Leads Us: Humor and Social Change" -- Production File, circa 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "Biting the Hand That Leads Us: Humor and Social Change", Circa 1988; cuid39303 (Box 165, 1 inch video reel 312_0158, Box 92, U-matic 312_0203, Box 144, Minidv 312_0683, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_20)
    Coordinated by Jesse Drew
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "Home Sweet Homefront: The Struggle for Affordable Housing" -- Production File, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "Home Sweet Homefront: The Struggle for Affordable Housing", June 21, 1988 (Box 93, U-matic 312_0206, Box 144, Minidv 312_0686, Box 174, 1 inch video reel 312_0184)
    Coordinated by Louis Massiah
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "Fourth International Women's Day Video Festival" -- Production File, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "International Women's Day Video Festival", July-August, 1988; cuid39311 (Box 85, U-matic 312_0073, Box 86, U-matic 312_0080, Box 89, U-matic 312_0118, Box 93, U-matic 312_0212, 312_0213, Box 143, Minidv 312_0634, 312_0635, 312_0636, 312_0638, 312_0639, Box 163, U-matic 312_0150, 1 inch video reel 312_0151, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_16)
    Coordinated by Veda Reilly, Janet Doherty, Susan Fleishman, Robin Mide, and Ellen Hendrix
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "Fourth International Women's Day Video Festival", April 9, 1989 (Box 140, U-matic 312_1830, 312_1831, Box 141, U-matic 312_1832)
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "About Face: Soldiers, Refugees, and Other Victims of War" -- Production File, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Deep Dish Cooks Up a Second Series -- "About Face: Soldiers, Refugees, and Other Victims of War", May 10, 1988; cuid39300 (Box 92, U-matic 312_0200, Box 144, Minidv 312_0680, Box 164, 1 inch video reel 312_0156, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_312_ER_17)
    Coordinated by We Are the City TV and John Luvender